Guide to the Edward H. Chamberlin papers, 1896-2017 and undated RL.11776
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Research and Notes, 1915-1975 and undated; 4
  - Writings by Others, 1925-1975 and undated; 2
    - Money Cycles, 1927-1963; 2 folders (Box 12)
      Includes reprints of articles on monetary policy and banking
    - Monopolistic Competition, 1932-1964; 4 folders (Box 12)
    - Monopolistic Competition, 1932-1963 and undated; 7 folders (Box 13)
    - Mont Pelerin Quarterly, 1959-1962 and undated (Box 13)
    - Non-Economics, 1952-1960; 2 folders (Box 13)
      Includes reprints of articles and journal issues in fields other than economics
    - Oligopoly, 1931-1959; 5 folders (Box 14)
    - Scope, Method, Planning and Welfare, 1925-1960; 4 folders (Box 14)
    - Slichter, Sumner, 1945-1959; 5 folders (Box 15)
    - Taylor, Fred, undated (Box 15)
      Includes portions of a draft biography of Fred Taylor
    - Theory - General Micro, 1949-1959; 2 folders (Box 15)
    - Theory - General Micro, 1940-1958 (Box 15)
    - Theory - General Micro: Leontief, 1950 (Box 15)
      Includes copies of writings by Wassily Leontief
    - Uncategorized, 1930-1957 and undated; 2 folders (Box 15)
      Includes writings by others that Chamberlin did not categorize
    - Uncategorized, 1934-1963; 7 folders (Box 16)
    - Uncategorized, 1935-1962; 6 folders (Box 17)
- Academia, 1923-1967 and undated; 5
  Includes teaching materials, committee, departmental, and other work for Chamberlin's professorship at Harvard. Files are arranged alphabetically by subject.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Access restricted. In accordance with the Family Education Rights and Privacy Act of 1974 as amended, Duke University permits students to inspect their education records and limits the disclosure of personally identifiable information from education records. Contact Research Services for more information.
  - Harvard, 1923-1965 and undated; 1
    Contains documents for committee and departmental duties and university business from Chamberlin's time at Harvard.
    - Biography, Bibliography, 1958-1963 (Box 17)
      Includes copies of lists of Chamberlin's publications and correspondence with Harvard University Archives
    - Churchill Event, 1943 (Box 17)
      Includes program of event at Harvard hosting Winston Churchill
    - Committee on Research in the Social Sciences, 1933 (Box 17)
      Includes memo about committee rules
    - Economics Department, 1944-1964; 5 folders (Box 17)
      Includes documents on department committees, curriculum, correspondence about department business, and materials from other routine business
    - Faculty Directories - Harvard, 1948-1963 (Box 18)
    - Harvard Appointments, 1923-1951 (Box 18)
      Includes documents related to Chamberlin's academic appointments at Harvard
    - Harvard Business, 1938-1950 and undated (Box 18)
      Includes documents and correspondence pertaining to routine university business
    - Harvard Library, 1949-1957 (Box 18)
      Includes correspondence related to depositing published writings in the library
    - Harvard Retirement, 1965 (Box 18)
      Includes correspondence related to Chamberlin's retirement
    - Harvardiana, 1926-1958 (Box 18)
      Includes documents related to current events at Harvard and the institution's history
    - School of Overseas Administration, undated (Box 18)
      Includes lists of staff members of which Lucienne Chamberlin was a member
    - Visiting Committee, 1958 (Box 18)
      Includes hand-written notes
    - Walsh-Sweezy, 1937-1939 (Box 18)
      Includes documents related to Harvard's dismissal of two faculty members
  - Teaching, 1936-1967 and undated; 2
    Includes syllabi, lecture notes, class rosters, sample exams, and other documents related to Chamberlin's teaching and Harvard's graduate program in economics.
    - Class Lists (Recent), 1959-1962 (Box 18)
      Includes class rosters and seating charts
    - Classroom Experiment, 1940-1967 and undated; 2 folders (Box 18)
      Includes files from a classroom experiment consisting of buyers and sellers attempting to coordinate a market equilibrium price
    - Ec 17, undated (Box 18)
      Includes lecture notes for course on introduction to economic theory
    - Ec 98 (Microeconomics), 1960-1962 and undated (Box 18)
      Includes course syllabi, assignments, and class rosters
    - Ec 201 (Economic Theory), 1946-1963; 2 folders (Box 18)
    - Ec 208, 1936-1951 and undated (Box 18)
      Includes lecture notes
    - Ec 209, 1949-1963 and undated; 2 folders (Box 18)
      Includes course syllabi, assignments, and notes for course on monopolistic and imperfect competition
    - Economic Theory Exams, 1939-1961; 3 folders (Box 18)
      Includes copies of exams
    - Economics A Syllabus, 1946-1947 (Box 18)
      Includes copies of syllabus and lecture plans published by Harvard Economics Department faculty committee
    - Exam Materials, undated (Box 18)
      Includes materials for unspecified exams
    - General Teaching, undated (Box 18)
      Includes reports on economics curriculum
    - History Lectures, 1940 (Box 18)
    - Seating Charts, 1951-1963 (Box 18)
      Contains seating charts for classes taught by Chamberlin.
      FERPA information restricted until 2038.
    - Seating Charts - Redacted, 1951-1963 (Box 18)
    - Social Science Course Lecture, undated (Box 18)
    - Teaching Diagrams, undated (Box 18)
      Includes copies of diagrams used in teaching
    - Theory, 1952-1962 (Box 18)
      Includes syllabi and other materials for various courses in economic theory
    - Written Theory Committee, 1963-1964 (Box 18)
      Includes copies of exams and correspondence related to Chamberlin's opposition to the adoption of a written theory exam
- Personal, 1896-2017 and undated; 6
  This series includes personal items of Chamberlin's and his immediate family. Of note are honorary degrees and awards received by Chamberlin over his career, personal items of Lucienne Chamberlin, and correspondence between members of Chamberlin's extended family. Files are arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Family and Personal Items, 1896-2017 and undated; 1
    Contains personal items and items of a biographical nature, including personal notes, personal travel documentation, calendars, awards and honorary degrees, and Chamberlin's diploma and degrees. This subseries also contains items from Chamberlin's family, such as some of Lucienne Chamberlin's personal items and correspondence between Chamberlin's immediate and extended family, portions of which are in French. Files are arranged alphabetically by subject; family correspondence folders are chronological, preserving original arrangement.
    - Articles and Books About Chamberlin, 2017 (Box 18)
      Includes copy of journal issue featuring article by Thibault Guicherd on Chamberlin
    - Awards and Honorary Degrees, 1927, 1953 (Box 18)
      Includes copy of notification of the Toppan Prize and an award from the American Marketing Association
    - Bibliographies (Compiled by Harvard), undated (Box 18)
      Includes bibliographies of Chamberlin's publications
    - Bibliography, undated (Box 18)
      Includes copy of a list of Chamberlin's publications
    - Biographies, 1967-1987 (Box 18)
      Includes correspondence with Chamberlin's family related to biographies of Chamberlin
    - Calendars, 1925-1964 and undated (Box 24)
      Includes personal calendars
    - Christmas Cards, 1945 (Box 19)
    - Close Friends, Parties, Obits, Tributes, Xmas Cards, Misc, and Limericks by EHC, 1952-1970 (Box 19)
      Includes cards, notes, funeral programs, and other documents related to friends of Chamberlin and family
    - Correct Dress Chart, 1927 (Box 19)
      Includes page from periodical "The Haberdasher's and The Clothier and Furnisher" on formal wear
    - Cruise, 1933 (Box 19)
      Includes brochures from French Line cruise
    - Curiosities, 1918-1953 (Box 19)
      Includes items of interest to Chamberlin's family that do not fit with the rest of his personal items
    - Diploma, Degrees, and Honorary Degrees, 1911-1962 (Oversize-folder 1)
      Includes Chamberlin's diploma, undergraduate degree, graduate degrees, certificates, and honorary degrees received over the course of his career
    - Distinguished Fellow, American Economic Association, 1965 (Box 19)
      Includes materials related to Chamberlin's naming as a distinguished fellow of the association
    - Engraving Plate, undated (Box 26)
      Includes metal engraving plate for Chamberlin's personal stationery designed by Chamberlin's brother Harold, who owned and engraving business.
    - Family Letters, 1914-1960; 42 folders (Box 19)
      Includes correspondence with and between members of Edward and Lucienne Chamberlin's extended family. Correspondence was sorted chronologically by Chamberlin's daughter Monique. Significant portion of correspondence is in French.
    - Family Letters, 1933-2003 and undated; 20 folders (Box 20)
    - France, 1944 and undated; 2 folders (Box 20)
      Includes items related to Chamberlin's travel and service during World War 2 in France
    - Gazette Obituary by Alex Gerschenkron and Others, 1968 (Box 20)
      Includes obituary of Chamberlin
    - German, 1961 (Box 20)
      Includes notes on German language
    - Grammar School, 1910 (Box 20)
      Includes copy of newspaper article written by Chamberlin at age 10
    - Harvard, 25 Years Recognition, 1957 (Box 20)
      Includes certificate recognizing Chamberlin's 25 years of service at Harvard
    - Honorary Degree, Boston College, 1954 (Box 20)
      Includes correspondence related to receipt of honorary degree
    - Honorary Degrees, 1949-1951 and undated (Box 20)
      Includes correspondence and documents related to receipt of honorary degrees
    - Honors Societies, 1920-1923 and undated (Box 20)
      Includes certificates of membership
    - Identification Cards, 1924-1932 and undated (Box 20)
      Includes university identification cards and a French drivers license
    - Iowa City High School, 1916 (Box 20)
      Includes commencement program and yearbook
    - Italian Language, undated (Box 20)
      Includes notes on Italian language
    - Joan Robinson and the Americans by Marjorie Turner, 1989 (Box 20)
      Includes correspondence between Chamberlin's family and Turner about Chamberlin and Joan Robinson
    - Letters After Stroke, 1959 (Box 20)
      Includes letters and cards sent to Chamberlin after hospitalization.
    - London, 1944 (Box 20)
      Includes materials related to Chamberlin's time in London during World War 2
    - Lucienne, 1896-1982 (Box 20)
      Includes Lucienne Chamberlin's birth certificate, marriage certificate of Edward and Lucienne, Lucienne's naturalization documents, and death certificate.
    - Lucienne: Budgets and Investments, 1933-1964 (Box 20)
      Includes household budgets and documents tracking stock investments.
    - Medical, 1959-1964 (Box 20)
      Includes correspondence from doctor about international travel.
    - Miscellaneous Information, undated (Box 20)
      Includes unlabeled notes
    - Newspaper Clippings, 1934-1965; 2 folders (Box 20)
      Includes articles about or quoting Chamberlin from various newspapers and periodicals
    - Notebooks, undated (Box 21)
      Includes unlabeled notebooks belonging to Chamberlin
    - Obituaries, 1967-1968; 2 folders (Box 21)
      Includes obituaries about Chamberlin from various outlets and a copy of Chamberlin's death certificate
    - Passports, 1931-1962 (Box 21)
      Includes expired passports of Edward and Lucienne, and passport photos for Edward.
    - Personal Documents, 1934-1963 (Box 21)
      Includes documents related to Chamberlin's personal business
    - Personalized Honorary Degree Storage Tube, 1951 (Box 26)
      Includes a personalized storage tube for an honorary degree conferred upon Chamberlin; degree was removed during processing and rehoused with other honorary degrees.
    - Plummer and Co., 1926-1929 (Box 21)
      Includes correspondence about ordering dinnerware
    - Portraits, undated (Box 25)
      Includes portraits of economists: Eugen Bohm Bawerk, John Stuart Mill, Fred M. Taylor, and Friedrich von Wieser
    - Red and White, 1915-1916 (Oversize-folder 2)
      Includes copies of Iowa City High School newspaper to which Chamberlin contributed
    - Religious, Prayers, 1954 and undated (Box 21)
      Includes copies of various prayers and religious writings
    - Rolodex, undated; 2 folders (Box 25)
      Includes rolodex cards of Chamberlin's and family
    - Rubber Stamp, undated (Box 26)
      Includes personalized rubber return address stamp.
    - Sketch, undated (Box 25)
      Includes a small sketch done by Chamberlin
    - Sorbonne, Honorary Degree, 1951 (Box 21)
    - St. Joseph's Abbey, 1956 and undated (Box 21)
      Includes personal correspondence with members of the abbey
    - Stationery, undated (Box 21)
      Includes copies of different pieces of personal stationery engraved by Chamberlin's brother Harold
    - Tobacco Pipes, undated; 4 items (Box 26)
      Includes curated selection of Chamberlin's numerous tobacco pipes.
    - University of Iowa, 1916-1920 (Box 21)
      Includes memorabilia from Chamberlin's time as a student
    - Who's Who Etc., 1965-1976 (Box 21)
      Includes materials related to Chamberlin's entry in Who's Who In America
    - Wills, 1928, 1961-1968 (Box 21)
      Includes copies of Chamberlin's will.
    - World War 1 and National Guard, 1915-1918 (Box 21)
      Includes documents related to Chamberlin's service during World War 1
    - World War 2: Documents, 1943-2004 (Box 21)
      Includes documents and address book from Chamberlin's time in Europe during World War 2
    - World War 2: Office of Strategic Services (OSS), 1943-2008; 3 folders (Box 21)
      Includes documents from Chamberlin's service with OSS in Europe during World War 2 and more recent documents about his service which were released from the National Archives upon daughter's (Monique) request.
    - World Wars, 1918-1945 (Box 21)
      Includes writings by others on European political situation during interwar years and World War 2
  - Coursework, 1923-1926 and undated; 2
    Contains notebooks and notes from courses taken by Chamberiln.
    - Ec 15 (History of Economic Thought) - Young, 1926 (Box 21)
    - Economic History, undated (Box 21)
    - Economic Classes, 1923-1924 and undated; 4 folders (Box 22)
      Includes notes and other materials from multiple economics classes taken by Chamberlin at Harvard and the University of Iowa
    - Gov 6, undated (Box 22)
    - Philosophy Classes, undated; 2 folders (Box 22)